Everybody here.
>> We're
going to do the Pledge of Allegiance and call to order on our regular scheduled meeting for Monday, 06/14/2021,
07:00.
Ready? Pledge of allegiance.
Pledge allegiance
to the flag
The United and States of
the republic
for
stands, which
>> one nation
under God,
the individual, indivisible
liberty
justice.
All. Thank you.
First,
we're
going to
move our executive sessions to the end of this meeting.
We're going to go to add and delete. We'll go to public speak right now.
We'll start moving it through. Jerry Wright, you're first up.
You're on mute.
Thank you. There we go. What
would you like to know?
>> Well, even before we get started, on behalf of the Board of Select and Jerry, I wanna thank you for all your hard work.
The Monument Park looks great.
Your event, went off without a hitch. Well, not without a hitch, but it went off incredibly
well and
you made Andover proud. Thank you very much.
You're more than welcome. We'll all clap. That's right. It
>> was a team effort
from everybody including Carol Lee
Mike Chief
Mike from the fire department
from from Paula from the slack from Amanda. That's helped me with the website
to
everybody, the whole town, Jay Tuttle, it came together, it moved everything.
It was amazing to see the town come together in such a short order and
everything happened wonderfully. Thank you. So I have to clap for the town of Andover.
There's one thing that I'd like to bring up real quickly is that we need to get Rob Pesot paid.
He has been waiting a week now and that is not Tom money, that's donation money that's in that line item.
And he needs a check like
this afternoon
and he's been waiting a week for it and he's been getting the runaround and I got not so nasty a call from him today
that this may be the last that he'll do for helping the town.
All
his work was done pro bono
and I think that we need to pay him for the materials. It was $19,006
The money is in the account and it's just a matter of cutting the check and that's all I'm going to say about that. I'll be picking the check up tomorrow morning. Is that right Jeff Maguire?
>> We're going to check on it Jerry. I appreciate it very much. No problem. The flagpoles
>> of the two new flagpoles that Joan Foreman has been working on It has been submitted to the town and we're ready for the grant money on that and when that comes in I'll notify
you that the grant money has been approved to do flagpoles.
So but right now I'm still going to meet with the
aid from
well I got a senior moment too Jeff.
But
yeah, we're still working on the grant money for our town
and hopefully about $7,500
We're still selling bricks.
Order of $7,000
was put in last week. They'll be here July 9.
So they'll be still coming in and
that money will go to revitalization
>> of our park. Okay. You had also said at a previous meeting just so we can be clear and get the right information out there that you had some type of fundraising
plan where donations would be matched. Is that coming?
>> Yes, I'm meeting with them Substantia Connecticut around July 1. Okay. All right. Thank you.
>> Who's next? Diane Grender, you're next on my list. Have to shut my door, so excuse me.
Go ahead, Diane.
>> You're muted too, no? There we go. I thought Amanda was in control of that. I'm sorry.
>> I'm all set. Thank you. All right. Thank you very much.
Jed, would you like to speak during public speak? Are you good?
I'm all set, thanks. All right.
We'll go to Kathy and Mike Plazzi.
We're good. Thank you, Jeff. All right.
Joanne Ebert.
Thanks.
Okay.
Shannon Loudoun.
>> Good evening. The only thing I wanted to note or question
is I noted on the revised
agenda or packet for this evening that the vote on the twenty second
may be occurring in the Andover elementary school gym,
and that might be a conflict with our cool summer program.
So I just wanted to note that to have the town determine whether or not that's actually feasible
before the vote is announced to occur there. Thanks.
Okay.
Valerie
Bruno. I'm all set, Jeff. Thanks. Okay.
>> I think we do have one other phone number. I don't know who that is, (860) 208-2345.
Okay.
That's Dennis O'Brien from That's me. Oh, Dennis.
>> Thank you very much for I joining
miss your picture. I do. Yeah. Well,
just got finished with a workout.
>> I'm all set. All right. Thank you. Thank you for joining us.
We're Okay.
>> Going to go on to five additions and deletions to the agenda.
I make a motion or I'm going to request that we
delete
item two, executive session for Todd Administrator's review. I would like to postpone that and put that back to
a special meeting sometime next week, and we'll get together with the other members of the Board of Select when I discuss that.
And I would also make a motion that we move item three, executive session for
union contract negotiations to the end of the meeting.
Does anyone have any other additions or deletions?
Yep.
>> Okay, Paula. I'd like to add to new business
the labyrinth that Carrie Crompton was talking about last month.
Have a quick update and want to talk about that quickly tonight
so eleven J
>> eleven j labyrinth.
All right.
Okay. Scott, do you have anything?
>> I guess it can be in the executive session this coming week.
>> Okay.
All right.
Jeff Murray, do you have anything you want to add or delete?
No, I'm all set. Thank you.
>> Adrian Mandeville,
I did see you here before, but did you drop off?
No, he's tall there.
There you go.
Anything for additions or deletions, Adrian?
You're muted, Adrian.
We
>> have the executive session on for Carol Lee, I'm told.
>> Is that correct? It's not for Carol Lee, it's for union negotiations.
We need another one for Carol.
Is Carol on?
Why am I
Okay.
>> So how about not?
How about now what? She's
not on. Why are we doing a executive session? And what are you calling it for?
>> She had some concerns about some staffing.
She
said she was gonna be on the call tonight and asked if we would do put one on.
Okay.
>> She not on the she not on Yeah. I'm not sure if she's not on. There's not not much I can do. It was up to her. So Okay.
>> So let's move on.
Do we're going have to vote on that. Does anybody have a problem with adding 11J
as a labyrinth and moving
the executive sessions to the end of the meeting?
All right. I make a motion that we do that. Anybody want to second that? I'll second.
All those in favor, aye. Aye. All
those opposed?
All those that abstain?
All right. Board and
commission presentations.
Do we have any on the agenda? It doesn't look like anybody's listed, Eric. We got nothing?
Eric, you're muted.
Not for presentations,
we do have some appointments.
>> Okay, so appointments.
So item seven appointments, we have a recreation commission,
conservation commission appointments, Norton Children Fund commission appointments, Economic Development Commission appointments, the Capital Improvement Planning Committee.
I'm assuming all these appointments are just for one year
or are they for two years?
>> So if you look at your motions,
their motions are all ready, they're all for two years.
Two year terms.
Let me get to my motions.
>> You want me to read it, Jeff? You go ahead. Yeah.
Okay.
I motion to appoint the following members to the Recreation
Commission for a two year term beginning on 07/01/2021.
Carol Lee, regular member,
Anne Marie Daigle, regular member.
Brian Briggs, regular member.
Kim Hawes, Cindy Murray, regular member.
And then I motion to appoint the following members to the Conservation Committee Commission for the for a two year term beginning on 07/01/2021.
Mike Palazzi,
Mary Anne Geil,
Hank Gruner,
Gary Geil and Carrie
Crompton as an alternate number.
I motion to appoint the following members to the Norton Children's Fund Commission for a two year term beginning on 07/01/2021.
Diane Greiner,
Jan Neumith,
Heidi Zeno Fontes, I'm so sorry I butchered your name, Bill Penn,
Charlotte Nelson.
I motion to appoint the following members to the Economic Development Commission for a two year term beginning on 07/01/2021,
Elaine Bukhart,
Catherine Magaldi Lewis, Kathy Palazzi,
Patrick Dougherty.
I
motion to appoint the following members to the Economic Development
Commission for an eighteen month term beginning on Yes.
>> That one's my screw up. Yeah, I was gonna add a different motion, but I never got the members. So just eliminate E, sorry.
Okay, nothing for EDC?
>> EDC you covered in D. Okay, all right. So that's
all I have for
that
particular motion.
>> Right. Does somebody want to second those appointments? Seconded.
Right.
Further discussion on any of the appointments?
All
All those in favor,
aye.
Opposed?
All those that abstain?
Good to go. Alright.
>> Caroli just texted me and would like to be added at the end as well.
>> We've already gone by additions deletions.
Does anyone want to sit there and
support Adrian's motion to put Kara Lee on?
Adrian, I need the motion to understand what it's for, and then I need my attorney, our town's attorney to approve that
language.
>> He has some personnel issues that she would like to address.
>> Attorney O'Brien, is that appropriate for a motion and to be able to go into executive session four?
>> Sounds appropriate to me. Okay. That's all there is. If it's personnel,
anytime you're discussing the
performance of
any town employee that
>> that is a That's why she's requesting it be executive. Yep.
>> The only problem is is the person you're discussing,
has a right to,
to have the
the session in open session if they wish. They're supposed to be notified.
>> Yep. It's it's actually it's her personal issue.
Oh, it's about her? Yep. And she's driving home right now from the town hall because she was there late. So hence why she wasn't on.
>> Oh, I have no problem with that.
Yeah, I guess that's okay.
She wants to have an executive session and it's a discussion about her performance. That sounds
that's unusual, but it sounds like it is subject to executive session.
>> Okay. Who wants to second that? I'll second it. All right. All those in favor?
Aye. All
those opposed?
I am opposing.
Let's move on.
So
we did that.
We have no resignations.
Eric, town administrator report.
Okay. Can I share my screen? Absolutely.
>> Amanda? Okay, I'm gonna pass
the host to you and then you just pass it back to me.
Sound good?
Okay.
>> However
I just made him a co host, so he should be all set. Thank you.
Okay, can you all see my screen?
Yeah.
>> Okay, so again, I'm just gonna hit the highlights
and the things that have changed since this was sent out.
First, we are still at zero for a fourteen day average of COVID infections.
It's the first meeting I've been able to say that and it's
kind of a nice thing.
So that's all I wanna say as far as the COVID update, it's been a long road.
I'd like to thank the following individuals.
The first is
Ron Bisson for his help with the Veterans Monument Park. I think the work he did was fantastic.
And Jerry Wright for organizing the whole thing. I think that was pretty
awesome.
I'd also like to do a shout out to DATCO because
we broke again our senior transportation
bus,
right when we were trying to bus everybody back up to the town hall.
And DATCO generously
loaned us a bus and a driver to make a bunch of runs so we could transport the people back.
So that was a
big shout out to them for doing that without charging us. They kind of donated that to the town hall.
So
on Wednesday will be
Trooper Ferrara's last day serving as the temporary resident state trooper for the town.
We have a new resident state trooper.
His name is Sebastian Neshi,
and he'll be starting on June 18.
So if you get a chance, say goodbye to Chris
and thank him for working for the town for the last
several months
and come meet Sebastian when you get a chance.
Jay's report will cover what's going on
in terms of roadwork.
We did a lot of tree work in the lake area. We removed about 300 trees.
There were a couple significant complaints,
but overall, not too many considering how much work we did.
I think we can potentially serve as the model for Eversource and how Eversource collaborates with towns.
So if we manage to accomplish that out of it, that would be a great thing.
So
right now, currently we've completed
crack sealing for the year,
or at least for this section, we may free up some more money in the next
fiscal year.
And a company called
Construction is in doing road shimming
in the Lake District.
We did have some serious problems
last week with overflowing
catch basins after the rain,
which
resulted in a call out from Public Works. Public Works also assisted in the setup and take down for the Agent Orange
unveiling.
Bunker Hill Bridge design,
they've
punched three of the four test core samples
for the bridge. The last one is delayed until tomorrow.
They had another commitment
on June that they couldn't break. So they'll be back tomorrow to do the last one. We managed to work it out with them to only do one lane closure at a time,
which was good because that reduced
inconvenience to the public.
We got a little progress towards the final closeout for Times Farm Bridge,
which has been taking forever,
but we finally got everything at DOT for final review.
So as soon as they sign off on it, we can pay the retainage to the contractor,
request 80%
of that retainage back from the federal government
and close out that project completely.
So I'm hoping within a few months that will take place.
We
received the paperwork back
on the Steep grant,
so we have a signed approval from DOT.
So the next step up is I
talk to the town engineer and we're working on the RFP for that
project.
The connectivity grant,
we submitted all the final, what we thought was the final paperwork to DOT.
They had a couple minor things that they wanted correct.
In the last six months, they updated the number of one of their forms.
So our plan set had to show that.
And that's basically about all.
I put the details in there for the
EZIQC
bid.
The bid from last year when you approved it to this year only increased about $1,000
Basically because the
contract details for that were settled before the big price increases in materials.
So we're getting pretty lucky
The on
other big thing that has come down
is two things. One, on the last day of the budget session,
the state restored
the $76,000
cut in ECS funding.
So our revenue will be $67,000
greater than we were anticipating
for ECS.
And the
American Recovery Act funding,
we got a thing on
the ninth
stating that the paperwork, final paperwork was due on the ninth.
So they sent it out the same day they expected it back. And oh, by the way, they notified us that the funding we're getting is three times what they told us they were getting initially.
So that's a good surprise.
Where it looks like we're now gonna get two allotments,
each allotment is gonna be $478,000
So
that's
gonna be a big bonus for the town.
There's still a lot of uncertainty
with the spending of that money.
All the administrators are unhappy with
the information we've gotten so far and what has to happen to actually spend that money.
Later on, I put in some ideas on appropriate uses I thought for spending that money.
Because ultimately, it's the Board of Selectmen's going to have to decide what their priorities are
in spending.
So that's a picture of them drilling on Bunker Hill Road.
This is what you get in the end. This is
a rock core sample.
This was the first rock core sample.
Modern bridges don't sit on
a regular abutment. They actually sit on pilings
that are pushed down into bedrock.
So in this case, these pilings look like they're all gonna be
in the 45 to 60 foot deep range for the new bridge.
These are the core samples that determine what the load bearing of the bedrock is.
And so it's basically
part of the design phase
for that.
And
this is
Matheson Road.
If any of you have driven up that lately, you knew one whole shoulder of that road had collapsed completely.
So as part of the shimming process,
we fixed up that corner and that sharp turn on Matheson
so it's drivable again.
So that's all I have for my report, unless you have questions for me.
>> I have I just won the the steep grant that was approved
is the roadwork that you're doing on Shawnee Mill and
Correct. That is for that.
>> Yes. Just letting
everybody know so they understand what it's for. Yep.
Okay. Good point.
Okay.
>> I have a quick question. Sorry, was letting you go.
We have a methodology in place to deal with
following up with residents
that have issues with complaints regarding the tree work specifically?
And I know I was kind of tried to cover one of those phone calls. I got one and what
was the resolution of that particular call? Do we know?
>> So that resident asked that there be an agenda item put on the board of selectmen's meeting so that they could discuss
their displeasure.
I basically,
Jay is the tree warden.
I had an initial conversation
with that resident and the second time I basically just asked Jay to address it because
>> it was gonna chew up too much of my time he's the tree warden. That's really his bailiwick. I totally understand because you know, was tied up on the phone with the individual for, you know, two hours over the course of two days, unfortunately.
And. Yep. Well, I get it but but what
was the resolution of it? Do we know?
>> I don't know. I left that in Jay's hands. Honestly, I haven't followed up with that. Okay, can we follow-up with that?
>> Sure. And do we have a methodology for following up with other issue with other people as well?
Like, I mean, if somebody reaches out to the town, whether it's yourself, my job, Jeff, whoever,
and we push them off to
the appropriate person, in this case, Jay,
I'm just concerned that we don't seem to have a methodology for following up with some of these people or some of these issues and they come back around like a boomerang, so.
>> Okay,
so
do you want
me to bring Jay on the next meeting to discuss
what is Is
he following up?
>> Probably we wanna come up with something, whatever Jay feels might be appropriate
or, you know, whether it's a, you know, I know you guys are meeting weekly,
correct? Yes.
So I mean, is that something that you guys discuss in your weekly meeting that you can then update us with?
You know, just give us a little running hit list of, you know, so and so went in a pothole, so and so had a tree issue,
whatever, whatever, you know, we've got a problem with this cohort on this road. This is what we're doing.
You guys are taking notes for yourself. Is there a reason you couldn't forward those to us or something, I would assume?
>> If you would like, I'll just have Jay include that with his,
his town report,
since he gives that to you every month.
If there's specific things on there that you want him to include,
>> that's fine. That's not I think anytime we have Okay,
>> Eric, just so we all understand, on this tree trimming, what was the main
crux of a complaint that there were trees dropped in a person's yard and they were unhappy with it?
Yes.
>> And that was their trees, not our there were we dropped their trees. We were over the boundary line.
>> So the
resident believe we went further than 10 feet?
Yes. Okay. All right.
So Eric,
at the next meeting or at certain time, can Jay just give us a resolution as to what was done? I mean, because I'm assuming Eric that the measurement was pretty close to 10 feet.
>> Yeah, I mean,
real problem, Jeff, is that
we don't take the time ahead of time
to figure out
what the roadway right away is for every single road in town when we do these things. We probably should,
but they're not all the same.
And honestly,
without using a surveyor, I'm not sure whether anybody can really determine whether there were her trees or our trees.
>> Understood.
And I'm assuming that the public works and when these trees were laid out to take, we weren't very far off the 10 foot line.
Yeah, that's a good-
>> To be clear, there's a lot of assuming going on here. I
to don't get into the nuances of this particular thing. That's not really my issue. My issue is that, as a whole, I feel like we don't have a methodology in place
for following up with residents issues. That's all I'm asking for. I'm not asking for this individual
>> particular Understood, understood, but you're asking about a specific issue. So Eric, at the next meeting, if we can sit there and have some type of understanding as to a resident
complaint, how we're going to handle them,
it doesn't need to be excessive.
>> Let's just have a basic standard operating procedure and we'll follow it as we move forward. Just a list of complaints that we're getting, what they're related to, whether it's trees, roadwork, whatever. So we can start tracking that. And that will also give us a way to be able to,
you know, see what residents are calling in and having issues with. So we know where to spend, whether it's these COVID dollars or whatever, you know, So we're putting them in the right place if we need to. That's all.
>> Eric, do you routinely
get
calls,
complaint calls during these tree cutting
sessions?
>> A few.
So I think total on this,
wanna say we got three complaints.
Four, if you include one resident that was annoyed that he didn't know there was gonna be a detour.
>> Okay, so
let's do that. And then Eric, maybe one of the things on tree cutting, and I know it's really difficult. I mean, cut 300 trees or whatever you cut in the Lake District, I know you cut a lot.
I'm assuming it's got to be incredibly hard to mark those in advance.
No, it's not Jeff. That's
>> what we should be doing.
If it's not hard to cut and mark those The
boundary line issues
can be addressed also
>> in different ways. Maybe not in every property, but
when it's in their yard, that's one thing. When it's in a, you go along Lake Road and you look at a lot of what was cut,
there was a lot cut in vacant sections
that no one's gonna be upset.
>> Well, just because it's vacant doesn't mean it's not on somebody's property. Think and to Scott's point,
we should have maps somewhere. Yeah. You know, like for instance, Boston Hill Road is consistent on the whole road. The boundary line is the town hall is the
stone wall. Is the wall there. Right. So though the stone wall moves in and out and the reference
is different, it's always center of the roadway
to the wall. That's it period on Boston Hill. Okay. And most other town roads will probably have something similar.
So if we get a you don't need to reference the whole road, you need to find a point of reference and verify it and then you should be good. Okay,
>> I don't wanna take up a lot of meaning. I wanna say one other thing. Eric, did you ever write up that article I told you for the residents,
let them know what we were doing with the trees
and the problems that we're having with the trees, and let the residents know that this, it's a huge problem that we're, this is how we're addressing it?
>> I haven't written any kind of long article
on
tree work lately.
I mean, did last year, I did not this year. I
>> asked you to do that, I don't know, six months ago, so that a lot of the complaints probably could be resolved even
before they started cutting.
>> Well, I agree with you, Scott, there. I think what could happen is though, if we mark trees in advance, we're going to do a lot.
Let's sit there and say you marked a tree
two weeks in advance of cutting, a resident is going to have time to be able to go to Eric and
consider the fact that maybe they don't want that tree cut down and maybe it's in there right away and we can discuss it and sit there and see what a resolution is. I think a little bit of prior planning you know, would help us make Well, here's a question. I mean, we know that residents don't always read the River East. We know that residents don't always look at Facebook. We sort of have this conglomerate of people going on.
>> There a,
what does it cost us to send out a postcard,
you know, to say, hey, we're doing tree cutting
in this, you know, whether even if it's a town wide thing that we send out to say, listen, we're gonna be doing tree cutting over the next, you know, couple of months,
you know,
if
you have a tree, let us know. But also, you know, if
you if you have any concerns, please, you know, have a contact number or something.
I'm just, you know, I'm trying to think of ways to manage this, because we have had a lot of complaints
>> that I'm hearing so. Right. This should be addressed the whole complaint thing. Right. The big problem every time you go out, it's cutting trees people get,
you know, very emotional about cutting their trees.
Whether You know where their boundary lines are and if you don't, you shouldn't cut the tree.
Yeah.
>> Right? So you're saying if it's on our property, if it's on our right away and somebody doesn't wanna cut it,
>> you don't want it cut. Is that what you're saying? There's there's rules and regulations about cutting trees, you know, whether you know Scott or you don't know about it. Let Scott finish.
>> Scott is trying to say that we should know where the right of way is. That's what he's I think so. Is that what you're trying to say, Scott? You know, if you cut a tree
>> negligently
on someone else's property, there's a fine for that.
So If you if you do it unintentionally,
or intentionally,
there's a fine
for the value of the tree,
that's,
you you gotta be really careful about boundary lines.
>> Okay,
so
again,
prior planning and
making this in advance would be
beneficial to everybody.
So getting
best you
>> can.
I mean, you came to my property and spray painted something on the tree and said, This is a tree you're looking to cut because it's in the town right away and I don't want you to cut it, I'm going to communicate to somebody.
If you don't communicate to somebody, that's fine. Now, Eric has, I understand where Eric's coming from. I'm going to go. There's a lot of trees that in a SWAT, that's a lot of trees.
>> You're
absolutely right. But I got to tell you,
in the past, when Eversource has done this, they mark the tree, they tag the door.
>> Okay.
That's a great Can chime in on this? By
>> the way, I just lost electricity here in Willamantic, but I do have a phone that's charged.
There is a the tree warden,
there's a responsibility to tag a tree if you're going to cut it.
Because the
person who
lives in the property that,
you know, is
actually owns the,
actually owns the fee simple right to that that that area that is actually the the town right of way. The town right of way is only an easement.
But but but if they if you wanna cut any tree in the easement area,
you're supposed to tag it
with a notice that they have a right to object
and a right to a hearing.
If you ask the tree warden, the tree wardens are trained,
and they they know better than I do on that, but I have dealt with this before.
But I've never I've never dealt with a situation where anybody cut 300 trees.
>> Yeah. And and the the that's the problem is the scale up because of this ash issue and I get that. But that doesn't mean we should be ignoring this completely. So
>> No. I won't. I I mean, it would like requires
>> if the law requires a tree that your butt that you intend to cut to be posted
with a certain type notice, and I believe it does. Now I'll I'll get that information for you for your next meeting or actually long before that.
Because, like I said, I've dealt with this before. I've dealt with this in other towns. I've attended
three warden hearings on these things,
But I've never yeah. This this didn't involve 300 trees.
But I would assume the law still covers it even if it's, you
know, a thousand trees as well. If you're if you're gonna cut trees in the right of way, they're supposed to be posted
by the tree warden. I don't know who the tree warden is, but
it probably is the Department of Public Works director,
>> right? It is. Correct. So I guess we're all in agreement that we have to do something a little bit differently. And by the next time we cut trees, and Eric, when is your anticipated next tree cutting session?
I don't have one at this point. Okay. By the time we do it the next time, we will have a better standard operating procedure related to this and do it correctly. I would like Eric to do what I asked him to do and
>> write up that
thing for the taxpayers and let him know what's going on. All right, so I'm gonna make a motion that we
>> request a
tree cutting
proposal
or management proposal from Jay to be submitted for the next meeting so that we know what the procedure is gonna be.
>> Okay, do you have a second? I don't know. Second then.
Further discussion? Anybody want to
make any comments related to it? No. All those in favor,
aye.
Aye.
>> Those opposed, all those that abstain, we're good to go. Five, nothing.
We're going to move on from the town admit. Well, does anybody have anything left on the town administrator's report?
Any other members? No? Okay. We're going go to Item 10, old business.
The
alarm monitoring for the town buildings. Eric, is there any update on that?
>> Yes, I sent you. You had asked me at the last meeting to go back and see whether they would adjust
or give us different options for quotes for the Andover Museum.
I provided those and those are in
the packet.
>> Yeah, there's also, I think there's a motion point on it as well.
>> Okay.
All right. COVID funding,
Eric, you did provide us information
that there's going to be additional money
spent related to that.
Can you provide to us all the most updated
requirements
related to this? Because I think I'd like I I think we need to look at some creative ways to utilize that money for the benefit of that the town.
So if you can sit there and send the most updated
requirements
or how they're
looking for the
use of the funds to occur on a municipal
level, that would be great.
>> Eric, is there something other than that 130
something page document?
>> I mean, so the federal government and state government both have documents,
but they don't agree with each other. Exactly.
Personally, I would go with the federal government since they're the ones coughing up the funds. Has CCM or Croghan done any breakdown related to this?
So
CCM
held a public meeting,
which I attended to discuss this,
but they just basically went over the federal
program
document without really answering
any questions.
So Sherry and I both attended that, and neither of us came out with more information than we went into it with.
So CCM is
trying to come up with more documentation
on what the actual requirements are to spend that.
Myself and the other town administrators
are struggling with that because we don't, in fact, I was talking with that with Mark Walter of Columbia today.
He's like, I have no idea what I can spend this money
I know I got a lot of it, but I don't know what good it's gonna do.
So we're all in the same boat right now.
They will have guidance that comes out. We've got years and years to spend this money. It's not like we got to spend it right away. We've got like till 2025
to even designate how we're gonna spend this. We're gonna spend it a lot faster than that, Eric. Well, I mean, that's
fine. And I listed you some things which look like we probably
based on the federal guidance, that we could spend that money on.
That's in Okay.
>> We're going to sit there and as a board, we're going to review options and be as creative as we possibly can be for the long term interest of the town.
And
we will sit there and get to that.
Anybody else have any other questions or concerns related to this item?
Okay. We're going to move on to 10C,
the Community Center
Building Committee Update Report.
>> Okay. So I'm assuming that at this point, we're not going forward with the fire or burglar alarm for the buildings as proposed.
Does anyone want to make a motion to that?
Yeah, I would make them.
Sorry, hang on. Sorry.
>> I had to turn the camera off before because my dog was chewing stuff on the floor behind me. So I apologize.
Okay.
>> I'd make a motion that we move forward on the fire alarm protection system. We need to update it.
>> All right. I'll read the motion.
I motion to
accept
the revised proposal
from
FPT
fire protection team for the Andover Museum fire alarm and burglar alarm combined fire and burglar alarm panel
except fire and or burglar and or both. So there's a couple of things in here.
What do you want to say,
Adrian?
>> So
there's basically
three options here.
Option number one, well four, depending on how you think about it. Option number one is a combined
panel.
I think it was a Honeywell combined panel. That's a fire and burglar alarm panel.
And the other option would be either
just a fire alarm, just a burglar alarm or two separate systems or the combined system. So those are really your options.
You had asked me to readdress prices because
you thought they were initially too high.
So I sent you kind of revised
pricing for that.
>> Eric, was that in the what packet was that in? I've got like four emails for this meeting.
>> I don't know. I downloaded it off the town's website
The other day.
I didn't realize they put out multiple
versions of this packet.
>> Well I've got I've got literally four emails all with different things for this meeting I'm just trying to figure out which one is the packet.
>> You have a
$10,434
price for
fire protection
objection. So that looks like fire burglar alarm. Then you have another one that's
$5,965
which is just fire.
Correct.
Then you have another one that's
$6,345
Correct.
So Eric, which one are you recommending?
>> If it were me, I would probably just do the fire protection
for the building.
However, if you ask Scott Yeomans, he said he would be, he would rather have the burglar alarm
because he thinks it's more likely that they would get robbed than
that the place would burn down.
>> Yeah, except the insurance won't cover if we have a fire if we don't have it, right?
>> I
don't know.
That's not a question I can answer,
at least not right now. Generally, is the case.
>> I mean,
I don't know about you guys, but $10,000
for a system
to protect a building that doesn't have plumbing
is
exorbitant.
>> So,
I get it and look, it's your decision to make.
You asked me to ask the contractor
to
look at revised pricing.
That's what they got back to me with for what they would be willing to do. I'm not telling you you should accept it. I'm just telling you those are the prices that they quoted. So, what the contractor did was take
$500 off of each original quotation.
>> Correct. And then give a second quote for, I asked them whether
they could provide a system that would do both so we didn't have to buy two separate systems.
So they provided that quote also.
>> And how long has this facility been without the alarm?
>> So,
I think about five years ago,
the previous
First Selectmen
got rid of the existing alarm system that was in there and bought this little homeowner special that sits in the middle of the room,
you know, because he didn't wanna pay for the phone lines,
basically, and the monitoring for it, and it was cheaper.
So what does it do?
The existing
>> know, that something's happened there.
The dispatch never calls the actual dispatch center.
They always call either Scott or myself.
But,
you know,
it's literally one single detector
in the building.
So it's not really,
you know, the reality is the building would be well and truly burned up by the time anybody responded to something there.
Eric, can I step in for a second?
You go, There
>> are two separate smoke detectors I'm sorry, heat detectors in there. One in the furnace room, one in the main room.
And there are two motion detectors in there. It is a cell based system.
They are supposed to first contact Eric or I to try to see if we can go down, in the burglar fire, they should call directly
to 911.
We never got a fire, so I don't know if that is their procedure or not. But when the burglar portion goes off, they're supposed to notify us first to check it. Secondly, they're supposed to call the state police.
It is not a quote monitored system. Again, it is a cell based system. When the alarm trips, a cell phone call is initiated.
The original system that Bob Burbank
caused to go out of service because he didn't wanna pay for the phone system
is still down there. It still is active if you pull one of the poll stations. It just does not have a phone line active to call out of the building.
It's entirely possible that that could be resurrected.
>> And so then we would just need to find a monitoring service that would monitor that alarm system?
>> I would have to see how the dialer works, but I believe it just dialed 911
and gave up like a recording location or something. Again,
it's been
far longer I think than the five years that Eric said. I would be surprised it wasn't ten years ago we replaced that. Okay, so can we find out if that's an option?
>> Because
that would be a heck of a lot less expensive than $6,345
or $10,000
>> What's the mod is
the monitoring though of the of both a singular number?
>> As far as I know, yes. But it
depends on what you mean by singular, I guess. Again, the original one I believe called into TN,
which is the fire department dispatch service.
And the one now goes to
whoever the cell service that sells the units, it goes to their center. Again, they're not actively monitored. These both dialed out.
>> Okay,
so we actually have to get a little bit more information on this. Let's put this back on the agenda for next month and get this done with. I mean, obviously,
I'm not going to want to sit there and
have us spend $10,000
for a combined system
if we can do it a different way.
>> Well,
let's ask another question. Are
we gonna do the fireside?
>> Why would we do the fireside if we can read all we gotta do, if the reality of this conversation is we have to put a phone line into that building and
reactivate
the old system, then let's put a phone line in and reactivate the old system. We're talking $40 a month.
That's
$500
Right.
>> We've
already moved forward on the public
works at this point though, right, Eric?
>> We
have scheduled
the changeover
to the auto dialers,
the cell based dialers, that's the first thing.
And we've asked them to come in and do a full evaluation
of what's in Public Works to see whether we can
reuse as much of what's there as possible
instead of ripping out the whole system and start over.
Okay.
All right.
>> It. I just want to make sure we're not slowing that down as while we're doing this. That's all. You
>> can give us an update on that as well as this at the next meeting.
Sure.
I'm fine with that.
All right.
It's like a better alternative.
>> So in other words, you want them to come in and
do reevaluate
the museum to see whether
parts of the old system
can be salvaged
is what you're saying, whether
we can connect to that system. And Scott, do you know what the age of that system is?
>> It's old. The original system is ancient,
probably
not as old as the building, but darn near.
Okay.
The cell system is probably ten years.
>> I mean, listen, you know, I sort of take the attitude on this that, you know, we're spending, we're spending a lot of time and energy resources,
kind of kicking this around. I think this is the best price we're gonna get to do it. I kind of just want to do it personally,
you know.
I mean, we don't have a lot of town buildings, we don't have a lot of things that we're trying to maintain, but the ones that we have, we kind of need to keep up on at this point. I mean, if the issue is that we don't have extra funds,
we should have lots of funds available for something like this, right, Eric?
>> Actually have lots of funds that would be available for this, but the issue is $10,000
a good investment for
what we're trying to do.
>> Well, don't think it's
not really just the building, it's all the memorabilia that's in there, right? Right.
>> No, I don't disagree. I'm just asking if the amount of money that's required for it can be
>> minimized.
I get it, but we're trying to minimize this to the umpteenth degree. As everyone just said, this thing is old as heck.
You know, at this point, I just make a motion that we move forward. I really don't want to spend more time, more of Eric's time on this or Scott's time or anybody else's at this point because next month, we're going to come back and find out it's 40 years old and it's garbage. So let's just do the darn thing.
>> Well, let's go back this way.
The system that there's, I would assume if we put in a telephone into that building, we'd have to be able to find a system that's less expensive. I mean, I put a fire and safety system within my office and it wasn't that much money. I just had to re update it and
it cannot be $10,000
But if you want to go ahead and spend the $10,000 let's vote on it.
>> I didn't get a second, so I don't know. Maybe dead in the water.
>> Anybody?
Then let's evaluate it at the next meeting. I mean, it's gone so long without having anything done. We got to figure out if there's a less expensive way to do that building. Agree with I agree for Scott's benefit. There's a lot of memorabilia in that building. It's something that we don't want to sit there and see anything happen to. But
that just doesn't seem like it.
>> Well, commercial panel they're looking at is to be able to locate where the fire is and all that fun stuff. It's definitely
overkill for
>> the location, but I mean, that building just in and of itself, if that building goes up, if that building has a fire start in it,
I think Scott would tell you there's not going to be a stopping of that fire.
I'll ask Scott. Scott, the structure of that building, if a fire starts in that building, what are we looking at? How much time do you think you got?
>> Not
much. I would agree with you. If it gets into the walls, it's probably gone.
>> Okay.
Now, we're not asking for that ever happen, but let's sit there and
look at it.
Eric, I would just ask if there's step
down version of a system that would work for what we're trying to accomplish rather than a high end commercial system for that building.
>> If there's not, then okay, next meeting we do what Adrian says and we spend the money to protect the building. Well, I would leave it up to Scott. Scott has been the caretaker down there. I think we should sort of go in whatever direction
Scott would like. You know, if Scott feels that we need both, then we do both. If he feels like, you know, we need one or the other, then let's do that. But
don't know the building.
>> I've stated several times that I certainly
would like to see strongly encouraged that we have both,
whether you need a system that can identify where the fire is. There's only really two rooms
in that entire building. There's the furnace room and there's everything else. Right. That I agree seems like overkill.
If we had something that tied into the existing
heat sensors, which one of the, at least one of the guys, maybe two of them said that everything there looked usable except the panel.
I agree with you, 10,000 seems like a lot of money. My position though is I'd really like to see both burglar and fire at that building.
Dollars 10,000
worth,
I can't really say whether that's reasonable or not. I'm not in the business. The amount of people that are down there now has really increased also.
>> Sorry. I think I think Scott is Find out find out next month then. That's fine. Thank you, Scott, for your input.
>> Can you so what am I doing? What is it that you want for the next meeting?
>> Ask them if they have a simpler system
that's not
that you know, that's not a $5,000 panel. Alternatives.
>> Right. And if we can use the existing sensors that are great.
>> I mean, honestly, if that's if that's where the direction we're going is we want to simplify the whole thing. For crying out loud, we could do something like simple safe that uses a cellular dial up. I mean, you know, we have, you know, we have a system at our house that does, I don't have a landline, it's southern with a cellular backup and, you know, it's, you know, $30 a month for monitoring does both. Adrian, that's what's down there today.
>> Right, if you want that, just keep what you got and don't
spend anything.
But what
>> I'm hearing is it's not set up correctly because
you two gentlemen are the only two receiving the phone calls.
So we got to find something that is set up. We can't do
it right. So let's ask
FPT if they can sit there and recommend something and if not, then we probably should look back at something like Adrian just suggested.
Okay.
I thought we went past COVID funding. Didn't we talk about COVID funding? Yes. We
have not talked about 10C, the community. I thought we talked about that. No? No. Okay. Let's talk about that.
Where is the committee currently on where they're at with the new building?
That we are going to build, let everybody be aware that building is getting built.
All right?
I second that. Adrian and Scott, where are you at it with it?
Adrian, what happened at your last meeting
down there?
>> I was not at the last meeting because I am not on a meeting
>> in the field. Tell everybody about what happened in the field. The field meeting Scott or
>> Brandon,
town engineer pretty much confirmed everything that we thought as far as distances and measure outs.
The committee agreed, I believe, to put
Brandon's plan on the website. I don't know if that's happened or not yet.
Amanda, did that get relayed to you yet?
>> I believe Diane Chiquette just sent it to me
this evening, so I can get it up there tomorrow.
>> Okay, great. So they'll have the site plans on the website
And we're putting together,
hopefully be out this week or next week at the latest,
the initial RFPs.
So we've sat down with Brandon and agreed to what to do for the RFPs, what we're looking for specifically,
We're gonna separate site work and development work
and hopefully have some numbers back. The plan was to put it out for something between three and four weeks
for RFPs,
so.
>> And you decided on the grades also when you were down there? Grades
>> work just to do a full walkout basement.
You know, at least we believe at this point they do. That's good.
I can't speak to what the committee spoke
over, but as far as the site plan, we're on track.
>> Very good. All right. Any questions to the committee members?
Okay.
We're going to go to 10D,
the Veterans Monument Park update on park
updates, the BRIC fundraising program,
the June 5 Agent Orange. I know Jerry reviewed a lot of this when he was in public speak.
The BRIC fundraising program is going to be extended and is still moving forward. So, let's sit there and see if we can drum up some more
items related to this. And then, Eric, I know that we had some communication about
the irrigation system down there.
So Public Works is going to sit there and assist.
Is that accurate?
>> That is accurate.
We still got some work to go to figure it out, but we're working on it.
>> Okay. And have we put the
irrigation of this out to bid or are we getting this contributed from somewhere else? What is the plan related to the irrigation supplier? Matt, Matt Cordner sent me a
>> text message and he said that he
has a friend in Coventry that's going to be doing it.
He sent me a text message. I've been trying to get ahold of Matt. He's very busy and I
haven't gotten back to him. Stopped down there three or four times.
He must be very busy so I'm gonna probably call that guy directly and see what his plans are. He's saying in the fall.
But I wanna find out what
his charges are gonna be, if they're gonna be any
and something
like that.
>> And Scott, what I would like to do is get him together
with Lenco and
us walk it on the ground and figure out where we're putting everything first,
because we still need to do the trenching down to it and get the electrical and we need to understand his low voltage needs
and where everything's going. So if that's,
as soon as you know who that is,
let me know
and we'll try to set up a preliminary meeting.
>> Okay, we should put this up all of maybe a chronology of this whole thing
so we can keep everybody to the going
on this.
You were in charge of that, right Paula?
>> Yep,
I was. So I can revise that, but I I just have to talk to everybody and get updates.
>> So I'm gonna try to call that guy here. I think it's irrigation wizards or something in Aventry.
>> Okay. And I want everybody to know that Scott Persona has been putting a lot of time in to get down there and water that grass. I know Jerry Wright also does a lot of it. But Scott, thank you very much for all you do related to that stuff. Oh, It is appreciated. It's nothing. Thank
you, Scott. Also,
>> John Hanfield has also gone down there and done his Andover Heart flower bed. Again, I saw him down there this week.
I know he's not on this call, but the next time you see him, you should thank him for
that
>> effort. Beautiful. He does that every year and it comes out really nice. Yeah.
>> Okay,
10E open burning permits.
Anybody got anything related to this? I know that
>> I know another big landowner came in right up to my house and
dragged me out of the house and talked to me about it again. He's not too happy.
>> I
can tell you I
talked to our burning official about this and after talking to him, and I thought I had relayed that in the email, but
I believe he's willing to he was very clear that he's willing to work with the owners,
you know, any and he's,
he's not had any, you know, any issues at all. It's that,
the one the things that he's running into is that when people want to do
multiple burns, they don't want to have the piles ready to be looked at. They don't, know, so that he can clear the locations and make sure they're done correctly.
So,
I mean,
I'm a big landowner too. And
after talking to him, he seemed extremely reasonable
about, you know, these issues. So I don't think there's an issue with the building permit now after talking or burning permit after talking to him. I really don't. I, I was generally concerned.
I did have a, you know, an extended conversation with him. I'm okay with it. If somebody's saying they're having a problem with it, then they obviously haven't taken the time to talk to him. Well, they're having a problem with it because they don't want to open up their wallets.
Well, that's their problem. I mean, he's
doing his job and as a town, we're doing our job and following statute.
>> So what it is. Is this more like another standard operating procedure related to burning permits and how they function?
>> I mean, he's following procedure,
he's doing it correctly, and he's actually trying to be pretty flexible. It's just people from what I'm gathering and what's even what Scott is saying now that it's just they don't wanna pay.
They don't want to pay to do the, you know, they don't want to pay to do what they need to do. And they don't want to be prepared when he comes out to do the look. So,
you know,
it's not his fault. And it's certainly not the town's fault if people don't want to follow procedure.
>> Things have changed. You know, it was going the same way for thirty years
now it's all changed.
>> Well, but you know, things change. That's how it works. People Look, the town wants it to be free
>> No. It can just reimburse Mr. Yeomans for doing the inspections. No one has suggested that Eric.
Right, so what I'm saying is the only thing that's actually gonna satisfy the landowner in question,
because he's chewed my ear off about this multiple times
is making it free,
because he didn't pay for it in the past and now he has to pay for it and that makes him angry.
So, the decision is basically do you charge or do you not charge? We charge.
>> We charge. Honestly, I personally
am done with this, you know, with this whole thing. I, I was definitely on, you know, on the side of looking into it more. I feel like we've done our due diligence as a town. We've got a very reasonable person doing the job. I don't think this should be an issue personally, but. Change
>> in the town, it's changed and some people don't like that. That's fine. Change is terrible for some people and it's the only way you move forward.
I'm okay with eliminating
that 10E from future discussions until we get public speaking, we hear from our friends, they sit there and they get mad at us for not doing it correctly, and that's okay. I've made mistakes before, I will make mistakes again.
We're gonna move on from this one.
>> 10 F, blighted properties. Eric, what do you have on this one? I don't have any updates. That was put on there originally at Jeff Murray's request.
>> I don't have any updates on that. Jeff, is there anything you wanna discuss related to this item?
>> No, I think we just rounded up all the properties and we were talking about the one on the top of Long Hill that's bank owned.
And the Okay. Options were.
>> Are we planning and zoning planning on putting something in that we can enforce as far as a
fine?
>> Planning and zoning commission is looking into some of the blighted prop.
>> Are we looking into was a fine situation, though, so we can, you know, push these people along?
I mean, we should be looking at a townwide ordinance, I think.
>> So Dennis O'Brien has suggested that
multiple times and has given the board a
proposal for that in the past. It just never really got acted on. So how do we move that forward, Eric?
>> Let's
review the ordinance and sit there and put it on next month meeting and get it. If we all can review it before the meeting and try to get it passed.
Believe we probably need to take that ordinance to Tom Meede.
>> You do?
Yes,
absolutely.
We have an ordinance.
I worked on it with John Valenti.
So it was a while ago. Okay.
>> That was a while ago, and, it was difficult to pass it.
There was a lot of opposition,
so it was somewhat watered down.
But we could I could take a look at it and, see what can be done to
improve it. And I'd like to,
know the fact situations we're dealing with
in order to improve it
>> Let's have in way that's gonna
more teeth in it so that we can do the things we wanna do because
I, for one, love town meetings. I'm ready to go back again and do it again.
And I think we
should sit there and
have this ordinance be as aggressive as we possibly can make it. There's
>> already
some ordinances
written
for blighted properties.
There's ordinances for collecting
for further sale,
there's ordinances about
securing
homes,
there's
ordinances for holes in the roof of homes.
There really is some ordinances already.
>> Yes,
there is, we have an existing white ordinance.
We do not have an existing fine ordinance.
And if you want to start putting in fines,
then one of the things you need to do as town is also adopt a fine ordinance.
And I believe Dennis gave you,
at least I've seen a copy of a proposed fine ordinance,
as well as a hearing officer and a hearing officer procedure.
So you would need to basically go to town meeting and adopt all three of those things if you wanted to add teeth to that. Am I correct, Dennis?
>> Well, there is a there is a way to adapt an ordinance that allows you to,
you know, create other ordinances where you can you can find folks.
And if the if you get,
you have to have a hearing officer in case they object.
The hearing officer gets a you know, people get a chance to have their case heard before a hearing officer.
And if the hearing officer rules against them, then they can appeal to Superior Court.
Rarely happens,
we had a fine ordinance that I put in place in Mansfield,
and we used it very effectively,
to do all kinds of things to stop
student parties
and it was very effective. The police were able to implement it without using the criminal law and
I know we have a blight ordinance here because I worked on it but it's not Scott. It's not it's not as comprehensive as it could be. Although I do think it I do think it calls for fine
that can be enforced in court.
I'll take another look at it because
I think it was implemented by John once or twice
fairly successfully
in the sense that he got the blighted properties blighted
property
somewhat cleaned up.
But I don't I don't recall ever being asked by him to that's you know to go to impose
a lien because you know it does allow you to lean property there which is very
>> there there is a lien on one property in the town because John
sent them bills for
over that blight ordinance
>> I believe too
No, maybe not. I was going to say it like a tax lien that you know it was
no, it's not like a tax lien I don't think where the where there's interest on it
a very high rate like tax liens.
I'll have to take a look at it, Scott. I haven't looked at it in several years.
But I remember when we had the hearing on it. Eric, I think you were there. You were chairman of the zoning commission. I remember you speaking at hearing. Well,
>> Dennis, you just
take a look at those and get back to us next month and tell us what
>> we're missing I'll give
you TMI,
too much information
like I usually do. Excellent. Thank you. Thank you. Okay.
>> You.
You. Ken G, the Memorial Day Car Parade Recap. Paula,
leader of the parade, please give us your recap.
>> Yep.
I wanted to say thank you to the committee again this year.
Thank you and goodbye
for now
to Dottie and Skip
Scagliola.
They have done a great job many, many years
with the committee and they are moving on to,
the next season in their life. So I just want to say thank you to them.
It was a great day, even though it was cold and rainy. We had people come out
to,
to watch the parade go by.
And we had fire trucks and residents in line and, it was it was overall great, great experience.
And I even sang to
the public on Facebook live. If you did not watch on Facebook live,
you missed me singing.
Well, thank you very much. Was
great Thank you, Paula.
>> Thank you, Paula.
We're going to go on to new business.
11A,
reopening of town hall.
Eric, your requirements or what you're thinking about doing. What would you like to do? What would you like us to do? Sure. I
>> included the same options I gave you
at the last meeting.
I would say at this point,
the
liability
concern still remains,
but I would suggest at this point, we would be better off opening the town hall
and just with the requirement that anybody that is unvaccinated
has to wear a mask
and that be for both employees
and visitors
and just keep it simple.
>> Okay, any further discussion on this issue? Does anybody have any feedback on this?
That's the only restriction you're going to have?
>> I mean, I'm open to other suggestions.
I don't have any,
you know,
No, that's fine.
One's fine.
Just asking if there's any additional.
>> Sure, I mean, there's a whole range of options
we can consider.
We could keep it the same way it is.
You know, we have the right to ask employees for proof of vaccination status if we so desire.
We can relax the mandate
indoors for employees who are fully vaccinated,
which I recommend.
We can
require visitors to wear masks in the building, we can not require them to wear masks in the building.
I mean, all those are optional now that
the only restriction that remains
in place from
the state level
is that unvaccinated
individuals are supposed to be wearing a mask indoors.
That is the only state mandate. So anything else
beyond that is just simply
us
imposing a higher standard if we feel it's appropriate.
All right, so you need a motion, Eric?
Yes.
>> Correct. I would make a motion that we reopen town hall
with the following caveats that we require
anyone coming to town hall that is not vaccinated to wear a mask,
that we ask employees
to verify if they are vaccinated or not, and any employees that are not be required to wear a mask while in the building. I'll second that.
>> Further discussion.
I I just have a question to the town attorney.
What if an employee
is not vaccinated
and refuses to wear the mask?
I didn't get the end of that. What if you have an employee that is not vaccinated and refuses to wear a mask?
>> I'm
not sure how that dovetails
with
you know, the union contracts or personnel policies.
Alright. I I have to admit you stumped me.
That that is impossible,
attorney O'Brien. Well, it's
>> be temporary. If you can take a look at that, that would be helpful.
>> Will make that the highest priority
that I have tomorrow morning.
>> I think it'd be positive to pass this.
I do think we're going to have problems because we're going to put Eric in a really bad situation.
We better have an understanding of what's required.
You're talking about employees,
right? Yeah.
>> Yeah. I think probably it's okay to say that, people
who, are not vaccinated who come to visit
the town hall for business
should wear masks
if they're not vaccinated.
>> That's
easy and then and they'll all
choose to do what they want anyway because we're not going to be checking the vaccination card at the door. The question ends up being for employees in my mind
>> that I got it. Yeah.
You're right. That one was easy.
>> I just wanted to give you something. People will love tennis. I will tell you that.
So
but I think it's a lot more difficult on the opposite side and it's putting Eric in a situation. And if we don't have the
right procedure That's right. Right way to deal with this, we're really putting Eric in a
I will have an answer for him tomorrow morning.
>> So last month we talked about maybe having them sign a waiver. So can we think and look into
based on what Dennis comes back with?
>> I mean, I've discussed
this fairly extensively
with the town's labor attorney.
Yeah. I'm
not sure a waiver
The does us any
real bottom line is
the town is still liable
for an employee
that gets COVID
on the job. That is just a straight workers' comp claim at this point.
It was something else under different rules before,
but right now it's just simply a question of
workers' comp and we do have an obligation to protect the safety of our employees,
whether they're vaccinated or not.
>> If Have you seen Eric, have you seen the,
they come out with a new statute this session on that
workers comp
not that I know of the no it was discussed I
heard some discussion
>> So I can ask my wife if she would know. There was a proposal that made it through the house,
but as far as I know has not made it into law that would have put the onus on employers
would have made it.
Yeah.
>> It would have made the implication that any employee that got COVID was likely work related unless the town could prove
it wasn't or any employer. I think you're right.
But that did not make it all the major decisions that would
have radically increased our liabilities.
So now we still have some, but not as much as if that had passed.
>> Right. I'll check on that to make sure, but I think you're right.
>> Okay. Well, this is a tricky issue. I think it definitely
has worker comp implications.
I don't sit there and totally see it Eric's way, but the law is never exactly how I see it because if they choose not to get vaccinated,
they should be assuming the risk, but that's not how all the workers' comp laws are written.
Especially if they
choose not to be vaccinated and then choose not to wear a mask,
and then what do we do?
>> Let's cross that bridge when we come to it. Are we not going to vote on this or are we going to vote on it? We're going to vote on it and if we have a problem, then we'll deal with it. Okay.
>> So we're going to deal with it after the fact.
Well, we don't know if we have a problem.
>> You have a problem. I'll guarantee you, you have a problem.
So
anyway, let's go. We can vote on it. Any further discussion? Anybody else want to talk about this?
No?
Those in favor
the motion as
open town hall with
restrictions
on
non vaccinated
residents coming to visit and
non
vaccinated employees required to wear masks.
>> Yeah, I mean, if you wanted to be more restrictive,
you could simply open the town hall but require all visitors to wear masks.
>> That would be one option if you wanted to be more stringent. We're at zero. I don't have a problem with being at zero. But what I have a problem with is
people who are choosing not to get vaccinated
are going to put themselves at risk,
and then they're going to have
worker comp implications that we can't control.
>> That is very true. My issue.
So, what do you want to do to change it, Jeff?
>> You want to require everyone to wear a mask going to town hall? No, I would personally ask,
>> and Eric has basically sat there and said that I would ask all the employees that don't want to sit there and
get vaccinated to sign a waiver.
Responsibility and that it was their issue
to not get vaccinated and if they catch COVID, don't sue the town. All I can And
what's the waiver gonna say, Jeff?
>> Don't sue me? If
you choose not to get vaccinated, you can't sue the town.
>> Well,
problem is that
you can't
sue, you can't waiver away the town's obligation.
That would be the same thing if I had a waiver that said you can use a chainsaw,
start naked,
right? And got all the public employees I to
>> get it, Eric. It's not like that and it's okay.
I mean, I'm just telling you what I would want done.
I would want the town to be protected because
we have choices. We could sit there and tell every employee they have to get vaccinated.
And is that right?
>> That's not right. We could. We could. We have that right
as an employer.
We would have to negotiate
with the union over the impact
of that decision. Correct. But we can make that decision if We we so could
>> and I would sit there and tell you that I
wouldn't go that far. But I would recommend
that they all get vaccinated and I would recommend that if they choose not to get vaccinated.
Dennis, what could a waiver say?
>> I
doubt that you can waive your right to That's what, yeah.
The state mandated
benefit. Workers' comp is, you know it's a state program paid for by employers of course but but you know that but
generally speaking there are lots of rights that you can't waive
eviction
rights stuff like that
let me find out I I don't like to speculate on something I don't know the answer to these are really good questions
and I'm I'm
my interest is piqued I'm very interested in finding out the answer
not not just for you guys but intellectually
>> very interesting questions so so so we're still at the position where we need to vote hey Jeff can I speak in here for a minute I
>> actually work at a large company
We just went through this
with
mask versus non mask? The company still has a mask mandate.
And if you come forward with your vaccination certificate
and you sign it,
you then can go unmasked in the company.
So the company itself still has a mask mandate. But if you come forward and you say, I've been vaccinated, here's my certificate,
then you're allowed to not wear the mask as an employee.
So that may be an option. I like that option.
>> I think that's an option that makes a lot of sense.
All right. Amend the motion accordingly.
>> Okay.
So the motion is that we sit there and open the town hall as of July 1. We open it with the restrictions that
everyone is required to wear a mask unless
they approve vaccination.
Are we going to do that for residents as well?
>> No, just for employees because they're employees of the town. I think,
I mean, every other business and
restaurant you go into, it's kind of on your honor whether you're gonna do it or not. But as far as protecting our employees, I think
if
they come forward and say I'm vaccinated, then they're not mandated to wear a mask.
>> Okay.
So it's just for employees.
Understood. I'm with you. I agree with that. The residents are going to be on an honor system and the employees,
because we have
a certain level of control are required to show us that they're vaccinated and they can then go without a mask.
>> Okay. Somebody Well, I suppose you could always ask the visitors
if they would show it and if they refuse.
We're not gonna make people Go big. Card around.
>> I hope we're not There's nobody there that can really screen them. Yeah. Right? Because as soon as you open the door, people are gonna come in and go wherever they're gonna go. So Adrian, since you made this motion, will you just sit there and craft it appropriately for the
revision?
Jeff, I would add Jeff's
>> I would
add with Jeff Marisa. Just write that into the motion. Please.
Yes.
Amanda,
do you have a reasonable
draft of a motion there?
Not quite yet.
>> Okay.
So we'll revise Adrian's motion if you will allow me to. We'll make a motion that we open the town hall effective July 1.
Residents are requested to wear a mask if they are unvaccinated.
>> Why are we waiting till July 1? It's June 14.
>> When do you want to do it? June 15. Tomorrow. Effective
tomorrow.
>> Effective June 15, we'll open the town hall back up. Make it the sixteenth. Give me one day to notify employees. Can we make it yesterday?
>> Okay.
We're going to make a motion effective
June 16 that we open up the town hall,
request
that
employees
to wear masks unless they
show
verification
of vaccination,
and then they will no longer be required to wear the masks.
The residents are requested if they're unvaccinated
to wear masks into the town hall when they come to visit.
Is that acceptable, Adrian?
Yes, please. Okay.
Somebody second that. I'll second that. All right. Scott second that. No further discussion. Let's vote on that. All in favor? Aye. Aye.
All
opposed?
Aye.
All opposes?
There's
no abstentions.
Jeff Murray, thank you for that information. Jeff, thank you very much. You're welcome. All right. Let's go.
So, we're now on 11D
senior center activities,
senior
activities, not senior center, but senior activities. What do we got?
>> So at this point, we're basically back to
pretty close to normal status
for all senior activities
based on the governor's guidance. So the young at heart is in the community room once a week or once every every other week for meetings.
We're doing trips, we're doing the Friday luncheon program.
We're looking at other programming possibilities
for the future
and try to provide them as much
activity as we can because everybody's coming out of a period of
really
limited opportunities.
>> Okay, that's great.
All right, thank you. 11C,
road notes from the Connecticut circuit rider.
>> Yep,
I included those in your packet.
The Traffic Safety Committee
met
a month and a half ago. One of the things the committee asked me to do was
set up a meeting with
the state circuit rider.
I did that, I invited you, Jeff, and I invited the members of the committee.
Nobody took me up on that, unfortunately. So it was myself and the circuit rider.
Basically,
looked at a range of roads throughout town
and she made a series of road specific suggestions,
both for intersection safety,
as well as
striping
and appropriate speed limits on various different roads.
I laid it out in one document for you to read. If you have any comments,
feel free.
I don't think we need to discuss it further unless you're ready to take action on any of that.
>> Okay.
I will look at this at our next meeting because I did read it, but
we should hold off.
We're going to move on to 11 d, letter to the auditor
regarding final fraud payment.
>> Right.
So
as most of you know, at this point, we've
recovered the majority
of the money
that was lost due to the fraudulent ACH payment.
The difference that's remaining is 5,000.
I would like to propose to Mahoney Sable, and I know they would accept
that we split that remaining 5,000.
So basically the town takes a $2,500
hit and Mahoney Sable takes a $2,500
hit.
But
it's not really my call to make that decision.
So the question is, where do you stand on that? And the Board of Finance is okay with that, but ultimately it's a contract. So I believe the Board of Selectmen should weigh in on that.
>> How much money
I'm assuming,
did we put this through to our insurance company and Mahoney Sable put it through to their insurance company?
>> So,
it has not gone through their insurance company.
At this point, we have recovered some money from our insurance company
and the bank was able to recover some money
from the account because
apparently the
person or the entity dumped some more money into that account from somewhere else.
And our bank grabbed that money as soon as it went in there and transferred that back to us.
So,
>> that's it. That's where we're at. How much was the insurance settlement?
I
think it was around
12,
around $16,000
>> something like that. So, our insurance company gave us $16,000
related to this? Correct.
>> And how much has Mahoney Samo ponied up at this point?
>> They haven't paid anything at this point.
If you agree to this and they agree to that, they'll pay 2,500 out of pocket and so will we.
But
Mahoney Sable has also agreed
to work on this year's audit,
even though
it's kind of questionable,
technically
they're required to be paid in full for last year's audit before they begin work on this year's audit. And they agreed to waive that for this.
>> So
just because I'm
We went to our insurance company and recovered $16,000
and Mahoney and Sable did not submit this to their insurance company.
That's what you're telling me.
Correct.
All right.
>> Yeah, I'm a little confused as to why it was our insurance company and it doesn't seem like
Why didn't they take any hit on this? Yeah, it seems like we got the short end of it.
>> I have a major problem with it just being our insurance side. Right. If our insurance goes up because of this,
listen,
there is a lot of blame to go around related to this issue,
but if Mahoney and Sable did not submit it to their insurance company, then we're the ones taking the entire
potential
increase
on the town side. Regardless if it was insurance money or not, I'm not worried about just the insurance settlement.
>> I'm worried about the insurance premium and what we end up having to pay next year and the year after. Is Kerma going after their insurance? Do we know?
>> I don't know. Kerma has their insurance number. But I mean, remember,
Karma has given up this whole cyber liability
completely.
So we're absolutely uncovered
July 1 anyway.
So our rates aren't gonna go up because this policy
isn't going to be in effect.
We're not gonna have this coverage
in another two weeks.
>> Correct.
But that's just a rider to the policy. We've That's not how had
a claim, so. Yeah. That's not how they're
looking at calculating our
cost to them. They're looking at the $16,000
as that's part of our cost.
Anyway, I mean, it's $2,500
I just don't think, I think Mahoney and Sabril for
the
hacking of their email system should have sat there
submitted it to their insurance company. Paid half.
Yeah,
exactly.
>> So,
you want me to send them an auditor a letter and just basically say, We're not going No. Pay you anything to deal
>> want to get this over with because this is how you settled it. What I am saying to you is that
it should never have just resided on the town side because while the mistake was made at the town side, the information requesting all of that came directly through their email server.
Correct.
>> Right? Yes. Okay. And I hope that we have standard operating procedures in it that no ACH changes are made unless calls are made directly
to the receiving party to verify changes to any accounts. That is the procedure in place now. Okay.
>> Is
there any,
is it possible to find out if our insurance is going after the Mahoney Sable side?
>> I suppose I could talk to the Hanover rep and find that out.
>> Directly Is through
Hanover or is it
Kerma administering this for Hanover?
>> No, I mean,
we've only dealt with Hanover on this.
Once it was initially assigned to Hanover, we've only dealt with their claims rep.
All right.
Any further discussion on this issue?
>> But even if they go at Yeah. I mean, even if they go after
Mahoney Sables
insurance,
that still doesn't cover the $5,000
because that's our deductible.
>> I don't have any problem with the 2,500.
I have a problem with our insurance taking a hit for that whole 16,000.
>> Well, I personally think that Mahoney Sable should be paying the deductible.
>> I have a problem with not only the insurance going out, but we're just incurring an extra $2,500
of expenses.
The money has already left our account On. For the entire audit.
So,
>> we are So, look, I mean, that's why I gave this to you. If your instructions are to me are to tell Mahoney Sable to pound sand and that we expect them to eat the whole 5,000
because that's your decision,
that's what I will bring back to them,
you know?
And I don't know what happens if they tell us to pound sand. I mean, we still technically
owe them an extra $5,000
that they've never received.
>> And
they sat there and I mean, listen, this is not an easy situation,
Eric, but if you get your e mail server hacked like that,
it's on you.
It is.
So now what we're after is
you went through the insurance policy,
they're made whole now for something
less than $5,000
We've lost we've sent all of our money out to pay for that audit.
So Mahoney Tsaibel is going to be short $2,500
and we're going to be over $2,500
>> Correct. If we do this as it's written. As it's written.
Well,
>> I have already I mean, I'm not a big fan of this one, but I understand that they are our auditor and that we need to keep
reasonably good relationships with them.
What do the other members want to do?
Anybody want to make a motion to move this forward?
>> We
were not the only ones that had negligence in this.
No.
Are we taking
all the hit for it?
>> Well it doesn't appear that Mahoney and Sable turned it into their insurance company to try to recover
anything.
>> I
guess I'm a little confused as to why we didn't get their insurance information and
reach out to them.
>> We gave their information
to Hanover. You
know, it's not my responsibility
to go after their insurance company.
It's our responsibility
to interact with Hanover
and give Hanover the packet of information.
What they do with that is on them, not on us. I'm not an insurance adjuster.
>> Do we have, did we get a settlement letter as to how they laid blame on this?
>> We
got a settlement
letter.
I don't know whether, I don't think the settlement letter
apportioned blame in any way, shape or form. There
was no apportionment of liability.
>> No, they just said what they were covering and what was remains was our deductible. Deductible.
>> So, this insurance company covered everything but our deductible $5,000
>> Correct.
Everything other than the money were covered from
Regions Bank
by People's Bank.
>> All right, well, let's just move it. Let's just accept it and move on. If there was no apportionment of liability,
then then you really can't fight who was at fault.
You know?
Okay, make a motion.
>> I'll make a motion that we accept the settlement agreement that's been by the insurance company,
where we pay 2,500 and Mahoney stable pays 2,500 regarding
the
fraud
settlement
settlement.
>> Somebody want a second, Matt? I'll second it.
All right. Further discussion.
All those in favor of the settlement.
Aye.
Okay.
All right.
>> The
11E
complaint from resident on Matheson Drive about tree cutting.
Do we have anything additional we want to add to this?
>> I do not. The resident had said they wanted to speak to the Board of Selectmen.
They were aware when the meeting was.
Are they on the call?
I do not believe so.
>> Okay. Let's go.
So,
11 F, Manchester to Village Hill upgrade project?
>> Correct. This is just for your notification.
We got something from
Eversource stating that they're potentially upgrading the overhead transmission
line in the power line corridor that runs through Andover.
Good.
Alrighty.
11 gs affordable housing plan grant.
>> Yes. So,
I believe Jed Larson
is on the call, I think.
Where is Jed? Yep, I'm here. I think Jed would be the best guy to speak to that. He is the chair of the Planning and Zoning Commission.
Jed, the floor is yours.
You're on mute. Yeah, okay.
>> So
by state
law, we're required to have an affordable housing plan by July
2022.
And we currently don't have one. We've done a lot of background work
that would help in developing that.
And we've actually,
through Eric's help when he was on the planning and zoning
chairman,
put a lot of things into our regulations
that would
support
more affordable housing,
but we don't have a plan.
And the state just recently
issued
a
document saying that they're going out for round two
Cities and towns can apply for a grant to develop an affordable housing
plan
and they're giving out up to $15,000
per town
to do that.
Eric and I got together. We
have had
a bit of an outline of what the plan would look like if it was developed by Bill Warner
who
worked on the
underlying information that would go into it as well as our last plan of conservation and development.
And so it's consistent
with what
he thinks we should be doing to do this.
The grant we would be asking for came in at, I think,
$9,600
So
that's well short of the $15,000
maximum that we could ask for.
And
I'd have to go to the
Board of Finance to see if we would have to do a request for proposal or just go right to Bill. But with Bill doing all the previous work, I'd like to have him take this and
wrap up all the information he's got to validate it with the current residents of the town. Doing some surveys and
get our plan so that we can submit that to the state next year and have that
not impact
getting any of the funding that we might need to get from the state.
Okay. So
>> the
grant proposal
requests that we submit a certified resolution adopted in the last sixty days by the town's legislative body, that's the Board of Selectmen,
authorizing submission of the application
and identifying the individual who can sign the grant application and administer the grant, and that would be Eric.
And so that's what I am asking the Board of Selectmen to do tonight,
and that would get us started on
working on our plan. Okay,
>> all right. So does someone wanna make the motion regarding
the resolution?
>> I
will.
I motion to adopt the resolution allowing the town administrator to apply for and accept the grant from the state of Connecticut for affordable housing plan
and in grant.
>> Do we have a second?
I'll second. All right, further discussion. Eric, just please make sure the grant application is for the full $15,000
If you want us to run the fees up, we can No, I want you to sit there and utilize it in a manner that isn't in
compliance with what you're doing, but it will benefit the town.
That's what I'm asking for.
>> Eric, why are you saying run the fees up? I'm trying to understand his side of it real quick.
>> I'm not asking him to run the fees up. I'm sitting there saying, if you have an opportunity to utilize those funds
that can be
beneficial for the community, I think you should.
Okay.
Is that what your question was, Adrian?
Trying
to understand
>> why Eric was saying that. Because they have a quote at $9,600
>> So let's be honest,
Bill wanted about $6,000
to do this. So, I bumped it up 50% to give us a little more wiggle room.
But I mean, I don't know whether you could really bring in a consultant
and realistically
expend $15,000
on an affordable housing plan for the town of Andover.
Okay. I mean, I'm sure we could find somebody willing to take that money. Understood,
>> Eric, understood. The issue is more not running up the fees, but being creative in how we utilize what we have an opportunity for.
We cannot be creative in how we use what we're looking at, then ask for the $9,000
and let's move on.
Any further discussion?
>> No. Are
we
going to use Bill Warner again,
hopefully?
>> Board of Finance will have to make that decision. Ultimately, that's a Board of Finance call because it would require
a modification
of their existing policy,
which requires
going to RFP on all contracts,
which we don't do regularly anyway.
>> Any further discussion?
All those in favor,
aye.
Aye.
All those opposed?
All those abstain.
Okay.
11H,
town budget discussion.
What are we discussing other than there is a vote next Tuesday?
And are we going to discuss if it fails
what we're doing? Is that what you're after, Eric? Yes, that's exactly what I'm after.
>> My suggestion
is that
I put in your packet
a
resolution
that was written by
the town's attorney
to set a provisional mill rate in case
the budget doesn't pass.
Do we have a financial statement?
No.
>> I thought Sherri said she just got one the other day at the town meeting.
>> Yeah, and she
was supposed to be on
this conference call to discuss that.
She is unfortunately dealing with her father who's been hospitalized.
>> Fine, do you have a copy of the financial statement?
I don't have a copy of the financial statement.
Why not?
Because I was anticipating Sherri dealing with that item.
>> No, but what I'm asking is, is it an issue because of Mahoney Sable? Is it an issue because of our numbers? What is the issue?
In
terms of
Don't
>> you get when she gets a financial statement on whether it's monthly, whatever, doesn't she give you a copy of that?
I don't always get the financial statement. No.
Okay.
>> Okay. So are again, are we waiting on Mahoney and Sabre to do something? Is it something that we haven't done? What is the issue? No. She got it. She's just not here to discuss it. And Eric didn't get a copy.
>> Just a reckoning on the bank accounts. Wanna know how much we have sitting there total.
Because I believe we have enough money that we don't have to do this
and that we could just
hold out another month if we have to.
>> I mean, all I can say is the finance director recommends against
that approach. I know you've said that before, Adrian.
>> Well, and when I asked her, and you know, I don't want to get into what I asked and didn't ask because she's not here to discuss and
say her side of it. But
my my, that is my opinion that based on our total account funding and how we're structured,
there's enough cash that we will not go through the burn rate that we can we can survive certainly thirty days, maybe even sixty days,
you know.
Okay.
>> So, but Adrian, let's sit there and just evaluate what's the downside.
If we do this, Eric, what's the cost if we actually set the mill rate in case the budget fails?
What's our downside?
>> The
downside
would be that
we end up with a final budget
that's higher than the mill rate we set,
and we would end up doing a supplemental
appropriation,
which would cost us money to do a second
round
of mailings.
If we
set the mill rate
and the budget goes down,
then the town essentially legally has the option of just refunding people in the following year
or sending out a correction
and reducing their follow on
quarterly payments
to match if
you choose to do that.
>> So in reality, if this budget fails,
we're going to have to sit there and do something either way.
I mean, because you're never going to hit this dead nuts, you're never going to get exactly the number and you're going have to refund people money or you're going to have to sit there and ask for a supplemental tax bill.
>> Correct. Correct.
How much does it cost to send out another round of mailings?
>> I
don't know that number.
800.
No, that's
a different, that's
>> right. Can we get from QDS the number that they would sit there and charge us? Mean,
know that supplemental number anyway.
Does anybody on the board really mind that if this budget fails, that we have a meeting on
the twenty third,
one of the days of the following week to say yes or no to this?
That's
a good idea.
Mean, we already
>> have to have a meeting anyway because we're talking about Eric on another day. Does anyone have a problem with that? No. All right. Then let's do that and let's move on from this and not sit there and subject ourselves to
a
rate that may or may not come into being.
Right. So
the 11i
is the public library chimney repointing quotes.
So, 6,200
Eric.
What are we requesting? What is the library requesting related to this?
We just do this to CIP.
>> So, first of, yeah, I would say just simply send it to CIP, make CIP evaluate it.
>> I've
talked to one the
vendors
and we need to get a little more information so that it's ready to go to CIP, but
let's just move it to CIP. Do we need to make a motion to do that or?
>> No,
we can, but I don't necessarily Is it necessary? We're gonna send it to CIP. Adrian, you're gonna walk it to CIP?
>> I'll be at CIP when it comes up. I've already talked to one of the Masons. I'm going try to reach out to the other one shortly. All right, excellent.
>> All right.
We had 11J
of a labyrinth discussion. Paula,
how are our circles?
>> Okay.
So I don't
want to have a long conversation, but we
talked about this last month real quick.
Carrie Crompton was suggesting over by the ball field
between the soccer field and the Hop River would be a great spot for a labyrinth.
She is willing to,
you know, come up with the design and work with us on this. You mentioned that it would be a couple of $100
and the maintenance would be very low. You just mow right over the stones.
I reached out to Bill Penn who is,
working with the boy scouts
and he said this would be a great Eagle Scout project.
So,
Carrie was, you know, I I asked her, I said, well, that's great, but who's gonna help you with it? And she's,
you know, she's willing to come up with the idea and kind of direct people, but she just needs help with the physical, part of it. So
I like I said, I reached out to Bill Penn. He's gonna be talking to the scouts the next couple of weeks and letting me know if there's interest.
Carrie said that between three to five people
the project could probably get done within you know ten hours
depending on how fast they're working.
So I told her I would would help recruit people
and
I'm putting it out there to see if this is something we wanna move forward with.
You know, we'll have to buy the the stones and
and I'm I can continue to talk to Bill about having the scouts help If the scouts are not willing to help, then we can maybe look to another avenue.
>> I mean, Scott, I'm going to ask you because you're down there. That parking lot, utilization of that parking lot for something like that, something you would like to see down there?
>> It doesn't get used.
I don't see any reason why,
no, I don't see any reason why she can't use it.
>> Okay
and then Paula, do we know the amount of money?
>> She was saying roughly a couple $100.
Alright. Well, you know, she was saying there's people that use the Hop River Trails there, you know, people in the soccer fields
would be would be able to use it. I
would love to see a sign there too. I don't know how much a sign would be, just kind of explaining what it is. So I don't know how much a sign is or maybe
Adrian can help build a sign of some sorts.
Okay, well let's
>> It just has to be kept away from the trail that goes into the river there.
That's all, so people can walk you know past it I guess.
>> Yeah, she laid down some flour. Eric did you I saw that.
Okay. So wherever
she put the flour, I didn't see the flour,
but that was where she was thinking
>> she was going to put that. Did I send you a picture of it? Yeah,
if you would, please.
>> Is
there anything other than a motion required for us to allow
that location to be used for the Lambert?
Eric, do you have any problem with it?
Nope.
Is there anything other than a motion? Because as far as I'm concerned, the rocks can be donated. We can donate those dollars
to make it happen.
>> What fund do you want that money to come out of?
Jeff.
>> The bricks. Do you want to give 100 and I'll give 100? Sure. Actually,
>> Jeff, don't you, didn't you have a wall just built? You got some spare rocks? Yeah, I got nothing. I got nothing.
>> We could jar some loose. Yes, I'm sure we could. But, I think we could raise the money for that. Here's
>> my next question.
Do we want
to put in our motion?
I'm,
my only concern is if we approve the money
and the Eagle Scouts don't want to do this and there's no help, I just, I don't want to.
>> Alright. How about we table this then until we find out if A, there's an Eagle Scout that wants it and enough people come forward to volunteer to help with it? Yeah, I don't think we need to decide tonight. I just wanted to kind of throw it out there because I'd hate for us to approve it and then nobody's coming forward to help do the project. Yeah, and I think in general, we run into this a lot where a lot of we get an
idea that somebody comes forward and says, it's a great thing we need to do this, but then there's not enough support to really make that work.
>> All right, hopefully next month
I'll come back and I'll have an answer from Bill Penn
and or
who, you know, Bill saying that Eagle Scouts don't want to do it, then I have some sort of idea if
we have to move forward with getting a different group of people.
>> Okay.
All right. Thank you, Paula. Let's move on to twelve, approval of meeting
minutes, Monday, May 10, Tuesday, June 1.
Are there any issues with that? Somebody want to make a motion?
I make a motion that we approve the meeting
minutes of Monday, May 10 and June 1. Now you're talking, I will second that. All right. Further discussion?
All those in favor? Aye. Aye.
All
those opposed?
No. Okay, good. We
received
a finance department report.
There's a
budget summary. Is there anything else that needs to be addressed?
Anybody have any questions related to any of the items?
Okay.
Eric, are there any
budget appropriation transfers that we need to deal with?
>> No.
The last thing that's going to happen is Board of Finance has to do, we got to give them the cleanup stuff on the twenty third to move all the money around by the end of the fiscal year.
Sherri and I are supposed to be getting together in a couple of days to work on that.
Okay.
>> Tax collectors report.
Collections for the month of May were $236,000
We still have remaining
$474,000
of uncollected taxes
going back to 2006.
259,000
are for the current tax year.
Anything
else related to the tax collector's report?
No.
>> Was there a percentage? I didn't see it. Is there a percentage listed on that? I'm actually looking for it right now in the packet. Of what? Yeah, the next page shows the dashboard,
>> which shows real estate personal property and motor vehicle
collected versus uncollected fractions.
So basically 97.5%
of real estate has been collected,
95%
of personal property
and 97%
of the motor vehicle
taxes have been collected for the current year.
>> It's basically the biggest number is still left in real estate taxes. There's $198,000
>> of uncollected real estate taxes for the current year. Can you tell me what page that's on? Because my PDF keeps kicking me out at 50. Page 85.
72.
That's
the problem.
>> Yeah. So there's
$259,000
remaining for this year.
Okay.
Any other questions related to tax collectors information?
No.
Assessor's report revaluation services are on there. There's nothing in the assessor section. Is that accurate, Eric?
>> That is the
assessor
and the
I forget what the company's name is.
They were running around on
Vision?
Vision Wednesday
and Thursday,
looking at all the recent sales.
John is out for about four weeks
because he just had shoulder replacement surgery today,
So we'll see him in about a month.
Okay, and when is the
revaluation
information required?
>> Not
for a while.
Not for till sometime in end August,
September, something like that. Okay.
>> Anybody have any other questions?
No. Okay.
We had other departmental reports, fire department report,
burning official. I don't necessarily know we got all of that.
Do we have anything from a tax collector report? Any refund requests?
There are no refund requests.
>> I don't see anything. Okay.
All right.
Any questions on the other departmental
reports?
Okay.
So we're going to move on from there. Eric, I'm assuming there's no correspondence?
Correct. Okay. We're going to move to nineteen to public speak now so that we can allow people to speak before we go into the session.
So Diane Greiner,
you're first on the list.
I'm
for my buttons here.
I'm all set. Thank you. Okay.
Valerie Bruno, you're number two on the list.
>> Jeff, I just want to reiterate what Shannon had said earlier. Can we just have a conversation about
election day?
Because I don't see that that was put down for AES for the gym and there is a camp that's there that day. That was an error, it's going to be in the community room.
>> Somebody
transcribed it wrong on the agenda.
The official notice has listed the community room. Great, thanks Eric. Yep, no problem.
All right, Kathy and Mike Pelosi.
>> Get on mute. No, thank you. We're fine. Thanks for the entertainment.
>> You're welcome.
Sloane, I'm assuming that's you. Do you? You don't have anything. We're not going to even bother you. You'll give us enough. Nick, we don't need to bother you. Shannon Lawton.
>> I'll be very quick. I just wanna note that at a CIP meeting and maybe at a Board of Selectmen meeting, I'm not recalling,
while I do not wanna run afoul of Carrie Crompton's plans,
that's an awesome possibility.
I had mentioned and started discussing
the use of that parking lot area for a town basketball court
and lining it also for a pickleball court to occur across from the senior housing facility.
So
before any action might be taken on that, maybe it should be discussed as anybody else having a plan for that
area.
It floods
regularly,
as we all know who worked on the soccer field.
And I was advised that I also needed to be in touch with our local herpetologist,
turtle specialist,
Henry Gruner,
before anything could be done in that area. Because I recall when we were working on the soccer field, that he was very concerned about the turtle population
in that specific area.
So just wanted to circle back and provide that information.
Thanks.
Thank you.
Joanne
Eber.
Go
ahead, Joanne. I gotta say something about that.
Okay, we'll come back to you, Scott.
>> Quickly, I hope in the future that when
you guys are looking for financial information that could help you make decisions,
then it's there for you.
We are in June.
That balances
that you can
looking for would just be readily available.
So,
yeah. Thank you.
Alright. Scott, go ahead. New finance director. So,
you know, I I understand she's got some kind of thing going on. Sure well, but you know, the information could be passed along to someone present at the meeting.
Okay,
thank you very much, Joanne. Scott.
>> Down in that area, it's in the floodplain, so you can't add or remove any material.
Okay.
So, mean the labyrinth I would say it's not a big deal but if they're going to put a pickleball court or something else in that lower area then you
would have to raise it up to get it out of the wet and you can't.
Am I correct
on that, right Eric?
Is definitely in the floodplain.
>> Recreational
uses are allowed in a floodplain.
I'm not sure a pickleball court is something that can't flood.
I don't see why it couldn't flood because it's not exposed to running water.
It would just be exposed to being submerged.
And
pavement handles that just fine. So in the future, it wouldn't be possible to build a more permanent structure there
without decreasing
the flood capacity.
Okay.
All right. Thank you very much. Lisa Kurtz.
All set. Thank you. Okay.
Carol Lee.
You're good.
All set. Thanks.
>> All right.
What
we're going to do now is we
have two executive sessions to talk about.
The first one we're going to go into is, we're going go into the one
that was related to
Kara Lee and the town clerk's office.
So
Paula, I'm assuming you're taking control of this?
Yes. Yep. Okay.
>> Then,
so we need to make a motion to go into executive session.
Yes. Then we're going to be asking everyone to leave with the exception of Carol to begin with, and then we're going to move into the other set of executive session and it will just be the selectman.
We'll be going from there.
AJ, why don't you make your motion to go into executive session for this? Make a motion that we go into executive session.
Okay. Second.
>> So I assume you don't want me in on this one. Am I correct?
That's correct. Thank you.
Okay. Yeah.
>> Are you gonna want me back in later or am I done?
>> I think you can be done. Think we're going to move into the next section. So Eric, I don't think there's any reason for you to stick around. Is there any reason for the other members of the Board of Selectmen to have Eric or Amanda stick around?
Are we going to have questions for Eric?
We might actually.
>> How about we text him when we're ready to get when we're ready to move on to that part?
>> Then he can can come back in. Eric, and we'll try to do it as quickly as we can.
>> Okay.
So you want me back in for the second one
where we're discussing the union contract negotiations.
>> Am I correct? Correct. Yep. Okay. All right. Peace out. All right. Thank you.
I'm going to stop the recording. One second. Yeah, go ahead. No. No, you're going stop the recording.